Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, good morning. We pick up on the
top today's דף Daf is פ"ה, Peh Hey, 85. We are actually
exactly on target. We pick up at the top of פ"ה עמוד
א', Peh Hey Amud Aleph, on the discussion had been so we're
dealing with מכה אביו ואמו Makei Av Ve'imo where it's only if
you make a wound. I mentioned to you the interesting discussion in
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi whether it has to be a permanent wound or
even anything that would be a wound on שבת, Shabbos, like even
a little bit of blood coming out. It's clear from the בבלי
Bavli it's the latter. And the בבלי Bavli deals with the whole
issue about wounding a parent for the for medical purposes to let
blood or it's incidentally when you're removing a thorn or a thistle
and it seems at one point to say it's permissible, but there's
another opinion that says that certain rabbis wouldn't allow themselves or their
sons to do it to them and refers to it as accidentally
it might come to happen that it would be like a שוגג
Shogeg on an איסור סקילה Issur Sekilah or even if it's another
person it would be a שוגג Shogeg on an איסור מלקות. Issur
Malkus. Of course, the bizarre thing is is that you know, it
would it's a case presumably where it wouldn't be a פסיק רישא
Psik Reisha number one, so it'd just be an אינו מתכוין. Eino
Miskavein. So תוספות Tosafos asks that question. תוספות Tosafos says, well we
have to assume we're talking about cases where we're afraid that during
the process it'll get to a stage where it will become a
פסיק רישא. Psik Reisha. But nevertheless, you know, one would certainly imagine
and this was sort of like the גמרא's Gemara הוה אמינא Havah
Amina besides quoting the ואהבת לרעך כמוך V'ahavta l'reiacha kamocha פסוק Pasuk
or the link to מכה בהמה, Makei Behemah, that this wouldn't as
חנן Chanan said wouldn't be considered to be מכה. Makei. I mean,
maybe the concern could be that if it winds up being that
the person made a mistake and hurt the person accidentally, but if
it's in the if the person's doing the right thing and it's
in the context of a medical thing, you'd certainly think it's not
at all considered in the category of מכה. Makei. Nevertheless, the גמרא
Gemara at least seems concerned with it. What's I guess particularly interesting
is that it even seems concerned with it when it's not a
father, when it's just a third person. So what are you supposed
to do, never do surgery on somebody because of this prohibition? Right,
clearly it seems that it has to be sort of like redefined
by this context. Okay, you know, one could make a distinction between
a third person where we're talk about injury and there it is
redefined by the context, and a parent where it's a issue about
I don't know, somehow not even injury but disrespect or somehow just
seen as the mere fact that the son inflicted a wound whatever
the reason was as we mentioned the idea of blood makes it
like a partial taking of a life or something. Anyway, the גמרא
Gemara doesn't make that distinction between a parent and a third person
and it becomes very strange. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara ended up by
saying that and how would it be permissible to take a splinter
on שבת, Shabbos, wouldn't we be afraid about the same thing that
it would come out to take out blood? So it said okay,
but that would be מקלקל. Mekalkel. Now מקלקל Mekalkel works for שבת
Shabbos to say that it's not a problem. It doesn't work for
a parent or a friend. The whole problem with a parent or
a friend is that you are injuring them, you are מקלקל Mekalkel
them, but for שבת Shabbos for it to be a prohibition, you
have to achieve a תיקון. Tikkun. But then the גמרא Gemara says
but then there's the position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says
מקלקל Mekalkel doesn't matter by wounding because wounding by its very nature
is מקלקל. Mekalkel. So it says okay, but minimally it's a מלאכה
שאינה צריכה לגופה, Melachah She'einah Tzerichah L'gufah, you're not trying to accomplish
it. Okay, so somehow by שבת Shabbos and then these these very
big תוספות Tosafos in trying to figure out מקלקל Mekalkel and מלאכה
שאינה צריכה לגופה Melachah She'einah Tzerichah L'gufah in הלכות שבת Hilchos Shabbos
according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon or whatever, which isn't exactly our
issues. But the גמרא's Gemara basic answer is that by שבת Shabbos
it's okay because either you're not in- because it's a מקלקל Mekalkel
or because you're not intending to achieve this result and by שבת
Shabbos has a specific intention. But it seems that by friend or
by a parent, it still fundamentally would be a problem. And the
גמרא Gemara sort of ends that way. So that's a very sort
of strange conclusion, you know, that is the conclusion I'll just read
do of the רי"ף Rif as well, meaning the
you know, here what the רי"ף Rif says
is
find it...
I can't find where they put it in this גמרא. Gemara.
This says... No, actually he
doesn't actually he doesn't actually
say... No, he doesn't say explicitly but he just quotes the גמרא
Gemara that these rabbis would not let their kids pull out these
thorns and says you know, pull out a thorn because it might
take blood. Anyway, it certainly raises a very you know, it certainly
is a strange conclusion because one would think that fundamentally that's not
included at all.
Yes, what is a פסיק רישא? Psik Reisha?
פסיק רישא Psik Reisha means that if you're doing something and even
if you're not intending it, if it's going to be a definite
consequence, then you can't say that you didn't intend it.
That's drawing that chair across...
Exactly, exactly. So the cases in the גמרא Gemara seem to be
cases of פסיק רישא Psik Reisha well because the גמרא Gemara calls
it says it would be an איסור Issur or it would be
a מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה Melachah She'einah Tzerichah L'gufah etc. and doesn't
just say it's דבר שאינו מתכוין. Davar She'eino Miskavein. If you're not
intending it and it won't definitely result, then it's not a problem
even if it does result. That's the general rule, right? Because then
it's not connected to you, the end result. Okay, the fact that
the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that means seems to imply that the
גמרא Gemara is dealing with cases where it would be a definite
result. Anyways, that's what we dealt with yesterday. Now we continue. So
בעי מיניה מרב ששת. bei minei me-Rav Sheshes.
So the student asked רב ששת, Rav Sheshes, בן שעשאו שליח לאביו
להכותו ולקללו. ben she-asu’o shaliach l’aviv l’akos u’l’kallelo. So we discussed this
as a hypothetical yesterday. Here it is as a real case. So
it's one thing to say you're doing a medical procedure where fundamentally
it's not a הכאה, haka’ah, right? So that's an easier one to
explain, even though the גמרא Gemara we just said had a real
problem, had a real question about it. But what about having the
בית דין Beis Din make the son their שליח? shaliach? The father
is deserving of lashes, so make the son their שליח shaliach to
administer lashes to the father, right? Or that let's say he has
to be put into נידוי niddui or חרם cherem and to give
a curse. Now, the curse example isn't such a good one because,
you know, presumably you don't do the curse in the exact same
way that would be liable, well actually it's a מחלוקת machlokes from
what I remember whether the son is... well רש"י Rashi says like
whatever, like in case of חרם cherem you might do it. But
even so, you know, there's a debate earlier whether you needed to
use שם המפורש. shem ha-meforash. I guess if you don't need to
use שם המפורש, shem ha-meforash, but I, you know, then it would
be possible that the son would transgress, although I agree with Michael,
you'd have to really see if the actual way the בית דין
Beis Din would administer a חרם cherem would line up with the
prohibition of a son giving a curse. But anyway, nevertheless, that's the
question: would we do it? בן שעשאו שליח. Ben she-asu’o shaliach. Now
what it doesn't ask is, like this could just be a question
like whether בית דין Beis Din would ever allow such a thing
to happen. Obviously it would be highly inappropriate, בית דין Beis Din
shouldn't do it, right? The more interesting question would be that if
בית דין Beis Din actually went ahead and did it, would it
get the son off of his liability? Because then he would be
operating with an explicit permission. So again, if you ask me, it's
better to have the permission to do a medical procedure than to
have this permission; this permission is actually an act of hitting and
cursing, it's actually an act that's supposed to, like, create injury at
some level to the other person. Nevertheless, you could make the split
the other way. You could say that here you're operating under explicit
license, right? There you're doing it for a good purpose, but you're
not having explicit license. And here maybe you're not seen as your
own person, you're just seen as an extension of the court. So
anyway, the more interesting question would not be would a court do
such a thing, but were a court to do such a thing,
would it get the son off? So let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says.
בן שעשאו שליח לאביו להכותו ולקללו. Ben she-asu’o shaliach l’aviv l’akos u’l’kallelo.
אמר ליה, ואחר מי התירו. Amar lei, ve-acher mi hitiru. So okay,
but since, so let's say they didn't have a son, let's say
they just had a normal person. Since when can anybody curse another
Jew or hit another Jew? So you're always, the starting point is
that you don't have permission to do these acts. But when you're
operating as an agent of the court, then that gives you license.
So if that's true by a normal person, it would be true
by a son. אלא כבוד שמים עדיף, Ella kvod shamayim adif, it's
better to defend the honor of heaven. Now again, I wouldn't have
defined it as כבוד שמים, kvod shamayim, right? I would have defined
it as you're doing it as an agent of the court and
you have specific mandate and a license, right?
Because כבוד שמים kvod shamayim to be, I don't know, you know,
we just got to before the whole issue of קנאין פוגעין בו,
kana’in pog’in bo, you know, we got to other discussions, right? Let's
say, you know, sometimes, let's say somebody sees their father doing something
which is a חילול השם. Chillul Hashem. And ומר umar says אין
חכמה ואין תבונה ואין עצה לנגד השם. ein chochma ve-ein tevuna ve-ein
eitza neged Hashem. So in order to stop their father doing something
חילול השם Chillul Hashem they hit their father and they wound their
father in public. Does that mean that they're not עובר over because
כבוד שמים עדיף? kvod shamayim adif? But it's one thing to say
you're operating for the honor of heaven, it's another thing that you
say you have an explicit license of the court. But anyway, that's
how the גמרא Gemara frames it. No, when you're operating for the
כבוד kvod of for the honor of heaven, it's permissible. הכא נמי
כבוד שמים עדיף. hacha nami kvod shamayim adif. So it should be
the same. So again, what's interesting about the answer is number one,
they don't make it based on explicit license, they make it based
on what is the purpose why you're doing this. Okay, number one,
similar to the דרשה drasha before when you were doing it for
a health purpose. And the interesting thing number two is, is that
they don't see a distinction between son and a, you know, and
a third party, right? Whereas again, by a son, it's a, you
know, the fact that there's a חיוב מיתה chiyuv misa might mean
that we conceptualize the nature of the problem as completely differently. Like
we said, you could understand why it's okay for a doctor to
do surgery and that's not a problem of he might wound somebody,
but it's not okay for a son because conceptual- it's- one is
conceptualized as an injury to the other person and the other is,
you know, by a father is a fundamentally different category. Okay, but
the גמרא Gemara here compares the two and assumes the same way
somebody else could do it to defend the honor of heaven, a
son could do it to defend the honor of heaven.
מיתיבי, Meisivvei, I'll ask you on this. So we have a מכילתא.
Mechilta. And the מכילתא Mechilta seems to be the purpose of the
following מכילתא Mechilta we're going to quote is: how do we know
that there's a prohibition to hit to hit a father, right? Or
to hit a mother? Whatever. We know that it's punishable. Where does
the תורה Torah say that it's prohibited? So
here's... Somebody who's commanded to hit somebody. Who's commanded to hit somebody?
The agent of court that's giving lashes. So the person that's commanded
to administer lashes. So that's the one place we know you're not
allowed to hit somebody because it says לא יוסיף להכותו מכה רבה
Lo yosif lehakoso maka raba that even after you even though you
have license to administer lashes, don't give extra lashes. So from there
we say, if you're not allowed to give extra lashes even when
you fundamentally have license to give lashes, how much more so can
you just not hit somebody randomly, right, where you don't even begin
with the license? So that's what it says. ומה
מי שמצוה להכותו מצוה שלא להכותו, Uma mi shemetzuveh lehakoso metzuveh shelo
lehakoso, is commanded to give lashes is commanded to not give extra
lashes. מי שאינו מצוה להכותו, Mi she’eino metzuveh lehakoso, somebody who's not
commanded to give lashes. So we're assuming this means a child on
a parent would never be, right, never be given that license to
begin with. אינו דין שמצוה שלא להכותו, Eino din shemetzuveh shelo lehakoso,
how much more so are they therefore prohibited to give lashes? So
this seems to be the basis of the prohibition to hit somebody
else and in general and to hit a parent in particular. For
us what's relevant is is that it says by a parent you
never have license to administer lashes. So that answers our question. So
the גמרא Gemara says האי
לאו אידי ואידי במקום מצוה, Hai lav aidei va’aidei b’makom mitzvah, we're
talking both in cases where the person who's getting the lashes initially
deserves lashes, is getting lashes by a court. הא בנו והא באחר.
Ha bino v’ha b’acher. So it means if a normal person is
giving ראובן Reuven lashes, he's allowed to give him lashes but he's
not allowed to give him extra lashes. So the son of ראובן
Reuven who couldn't give even though ראובן Reuven is deserving lashes, ראובן's
Reuven son would never be allowed to give them. How much more
so is ראובן's Reuven son prohibited to hit his father? Okay, so
that seems to show answer our question that a son would never
be be the one to administer lashes to a father. So the
גמרא Gemara says לא, Lo, no, you're making it too complicated, says
the גמרא. Gemara. אידי ואידי לא שנא בנו ולא שנא אחר. Aidei
va’aidei lo shna b’no v’lo shna acher. We're not talking about son
versus another person. What we're talking about is, I think Michael you
were suggesting this in your half-comment, which is how do we know
that any random person is forbidden to hit somebody else? So the
answer is, well, if when you're giving lashes to a person as
a שליח בית דין shaliach beis din you can't give extra lashes,
how much more so when you're not giving lashes to a person
to begin with are you not allowed to hit somebody? Okay. אידי
ואידי לא שנא בנו ולא שנא אחר ולא קשיא כאן במקום מצוה
כאן שלא במקום מצוה. Aidei va’aidei lo shna b’no v’lo shna acher
v’lo kashya kan b’makom mitzvah kan shelo b’makom mitzvah. It's whether you
fundamentally are obligated to give lashes in the first place or not.
והכי קתני, V’hachi katani, and here's how to read it. ומה במקום
מצוה, Uma b’makom mitzvah, when it's a case of a מצוה mitzvah
to give lashes, the person is deserving of lashes and the court
שמצוה להכותו, shemetzuveh lehakoso, you're commanded to give lashes to ראובן, Reuven,
מצוה שלא להכותו, metzuveh shelo lehakoso, you're commanded to not give him
extra lashes. שלא במקום מצוה, Shelo b’makom mitzvah, when ראובן Reuven isn't
deserving of lashes, he's just a guy you met in a bar
and got into a fight with, okay, maybe you think he's deserving
lashes, but anyway במקום
שלא במקום מצוה שאינו מצוה להכותו אינו דין שמצוה שלא להכותו. b’makom
shelo b’makom mitzvah she’eino metzuveh lehakoso eino din shemetzuveh shelo lehakoso. So
when there's no obligation to give him lashes, how much more so
are you forbidden to do so, meaning so it's a general basis
of how do we know you're not allowed to hit a fellow
Jew because it says לא יוסיף להכותו. lo yosif lehakoso. And since
that's a פסוק pasuk even in the context of lashes, how much
more so is לא יוסיף להכותו lo yosif lehakoso in a context
where there's no מצוה mitzvah of lashes to begin with? But it's
not talking about a son and a father, it's irrelevant for our
discussion. Okay. תא
שמע, Ta shma, come in here. By the way I should say
parenthetically that
that is the basis also for a son or daughter not to
give lashes to a parent is the same generic prohibition for anybody
to hit a fellow Jew is also used as the specific prohibition
for a child to hit a father or mother.
Me in the בית דין Beis Din or you're saying go ahead,
you know, you have our permission and it's actually an איסור, issur,
it would be an איסור דאורייתא, issur de’oraisa, is that what you're
saying the גמרא Gemara is saying right now?
What do you mean? No I was just making a parenthetical comment
that in general when a child hits a parent we know the
תורה Torah says it's חייב מיתה, chayav misa, where do we say
that it's prohibited? So it's for the same generic prohibition as hitting
anybody.
Okay but then back to this question like we
don't have an answer yet to this question. Okay תא שמע, ta
shma, come in here. היוצא ליהרג, Hayotzei leihareg, somebody is being taken
out to be executed. Okay ראובן Reuven has committed a חיוב מיתה
chiyuv misa and he's being taken out to be executed. Okay.
ובא בנו והכהו וקיללו. Uva b’no v’hika’u v’kilelo. So his son comes
and hits him and curses him. You can understand the motivation, right,
because he wants to basically disavow himself of whatever his father's sins
or crimes are, okay, or let's say actually the sin was something
against the family, then you would certainly understand.
Right,
your whole life you're not allowed to hit a parent, now you
have a chance. Okay anyway חייב, chayav, except that it says no,
you're actually you're not allowed, you're
חייב. chayav. בא אחר והכהו וקיללו, Ba acher v’hika’u v’kilelo, if a
third-party person did it, פטור. patur. He's exempt even though, right, that
if you hit somebody you have to pay monetary fines or if
it's not שווה פרוטה shaveh prutah as we'll see in a minute
you get lashes, if you curse somebody... Right, that's also prohibited, right?
You get lashes or whatever. Here you're exempt. So ורמינן בה, v-raminan
bah, מאי שנא בנו מאי שנא אחר? mai shna bno mai shna
acher? What difference does it make? If after the person is has
like the death penalty passed on them, you know, maybe it's like
they lose all halachic legal status, why should the son still be
חייב chayav and the third party not?
That is a good point, right? If you actually kill this person,
wouldn't be, you know, nothing, we'd get lashes?
We don't know, we don't know, we don't know why their status
is different just because they have the death penalty being taken out
to be executed. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara does. Okay. At
one stage in this גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא Gemara says he's גברא
קטילא, gavra katila, he's like he's already like, I've used that phrase
before, dead man walking, right? But how what really is the scope
of that legal of the implications of that is not clear. Let's
see exactly.
Doesn't the בית דין מחזרת לזכות Beit Din mechazeret lizchut also?
Right, well that's a good, that's a very good point too. Okay,
so let's see what the implications are.
Isn't he considered to be dead when he's hanging there? Do they
have to pay respect to that person?
Exactly. All right, so all right, all good questions. Let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, the גמרא Gemara frames the question though
as what's the difference between the son and a different person. דאמר
רב חסדא מסרבין בו לצאת ואינו יוצא. D'amar Rav Chisda mesarvin bo
latzeit ve-eino yotzei. Ah,
here's the reason. The reason you're cursing him and hitting him is
because he's refusing, can you imagine it, he doesn't want to go
up to the gal, what's it called, is that the gallows where
they hang them from? Okay, you know, he's trying to like,
he's using all of his effort, he's not being so cooperative, right,
and we're trying to שלעפ shlep him out to do סקילה skila
or חנק chenek or whatever it is and he's resisting. So in
order to get him along you gotta kick him, you curse him,
you yell at him. Now again, just because you're yelling at him
does that mean you have to technically do what is considered a
קללה klala according to, you know, the biblical prohibition of a קללה?
klala? But you might understand why you have to hit him, right,
you have to you know you have to he's grabbing onto something,
you have to yank him away. Okay, so that's the case. And
that's why a normal person has license to do it as a
agent of the court. But we assuming that, right, walks around and
wouldn't be, but we assume that the son would not be an
agent of the court, okay, and that's the difference. ואינו יוצא. ve-eino
yotzei. So מסרבין בו לצאת ואינו יוצא. mesarvin bo latzeit ve-eino yotzei.
ורב
ששת מוקי לה בשאין מסרבין בו לצאת. v-Rav Sheshet muki la be-she-ein
mesarvin bo latzeit. Okay, now according to that answer though, that seems
to answer our question. That we a third person or you know
a stranger obviously you make them an agent to give lashes or
here it's not lashes, but to if the court needs to sort
of beat this person up in order to bring him to his
execution to use force, so they'll assign that job to somebody. But
a son they would not do it. Now again, I'm assuming because
it's less of an interesting point to say the court would just
choose not to make the son that position. I assume the point
is that even if the court had unwittingly given that position to
the son, that would not give the son license. Now you could
still even within that you could ask the question: is the son
operating as an agent of the court if the court assigns him
and nevertheless would violate when he would do these things? Or do
we say that even if he is made an agent by the
court, objectively that agency is not binding, meaning,
הלכה Halacha never recognizes somebody in that role as an agent of
the court to do something like to the father? But that seems
to be the point, okay? So then you understand so that answers
our question. The son as an agent of the court does not
have the license to do these things to his father. Okay, so
that's a very nice elegant answer to our question. But we are
resisting that answer just like the guy resisting, anyway, so רב ששת
Rav Sheshet was the one asked this question and he says you
know this ברייתא braita might not prove it, it might be a
different case. Okay, as opposed to the way you just read it
where it gives an answer to our question. ורב ששת אמר, v-Rav
Sheshet amar, where were we? רב ששת מוקי לה בשאין מסרבין בו
לצאת. Rav Sheshet muki la be-she-ein mesarvin bo latzeit.
It's not the case that the guy is resisting. Okay, אי הכי
אחר נמי? ei hachi acher nami? So then okay so then we
understand why the son has transgressed, why has the third party not
transgressed? So it says אחר גברא קטילא הוא. acher gavra katila hu.
By a third party this person is considered already to be dead.
Okay, and therefore if he's already considered to be dead, now how
far would you take that? Would it mean that you wouldn't be
חייב chayav if you killed him or whatever? Right now let's see
where the גמרא Gemara goes with it. But of course the question
is going to be with all these answers, any answer you give
about the third person should then apply to the son. Okay. So
it says אחר גברא קטילא הוא. acher gavra katila hu. ואמר רב
ששת, v-amar Rav Sheshet, what do you mean? So presumably what we
assume that means, let's deal not with the case yet of cursing,
but let's deal with the case of hitting. So if you hit
him you're not liable for injury because since he's about that you
actually understand. The guy's about to be executed, how could you be
liable to him for bodily injury if he's about to be executed,
right? Like he's about to lose rights to his life altogether. Now
you could still say for the five minutes between now and then,
you know, but okay, but you understand, right? It's like let's say,
you know, let's say, you know, I mean the גמרא Gemara actually
in בבא קמא Bava Kamma has these cases. Your pot was thrown
off a roof and it was about to hit the ground and
before it hit the ground, you know, I tipped it in mid-flight.
Okay, would I be חייב chayav for מזיק? mazik? So you could
say no, something that's about to be destroyed it no longer has
any value, I'm not חייב chayav for מזיק. mazik. Somebody who is
hanging out about to be executed, right, maybe I would not be
חייב chayav for any injury I did to the person. Of course
there could still be a difference between the physical injury... if the
body's about to be destroyed and how about this pain and suffering?
Right, that's also a payment. How about what the גמרא Gemara is
going to deal with is how about the embarrassment? Right, the embarrassment
is still a reality even if the loss of, you know, limb
is not a reality because he's about to lose his life. There's
other things that are also that, you know, that the analogy to
the flying pot, to the dropped pot would not be comparable. Yeah,
Janos.
Right, exactly. So that seems to be the גמרא's Gemara answer. So
before we get to the difference what's the difference between the son
and the different person, if the case is that you're exempt because
the person's body now no longer has any value, so the גמרא
Gemara says אי הכי ee hachi but the גמרא Gemara says one
minute. ואמר רב ששת בשת שהוא ישן ומת חייב. Ve'amar Rav Sheshet:
Boshet shehu yashen u'met chayav.
You embarrass somebody in their sleep. Okay, and like you spat on
somebody in their sleep. Not just embarrassing by words, it's not a
tort. But if you actually do a physical act, okay, so there's
a group of people around and you're making fun of this sleeping
person and somebody spat on him, okay, and that would actually have
to pay, you know,
embarrassment, בשת. boshet. But then the guy died before he woke up.
So you could say he never experienced the בשת. boshet. Why do
you have to pay? So no, the הלכה halakha is חייב. chayav.
Why are you חייב? chayav? Because the embarrassment that comes to the
family. Okay, so here's somebody who never experienced it and you have
to pay. So how should that be any different? This guy, yes,
he's going to die but he's still he's actually even experiencing it.
And there's and you know and even if he's not around to
collect, the family's around to collect, which is basically a way of
saying like look, we get that he's about to be executed but
that doesn't mean that there isn't embarrassment and it doesn't mean that
there isn't pain. So why should a normal person be exempt? הכא
במאי עסקינן בשהכהו הכה שאין בה שוה פרוטה. Hacha be-mai askinan bishe-hika'u
hakah she'ein bah shaveh prutah. Fine. He hit him in a way
that it's not a it's not worth a penny. The damage. Now
why should that be make things better? Well as soon as the
damage is not worth a penny you take it out of the
question of compensation and you bring it into the discussion of a
prohibition, right? We just learned before you're not allowed to hit somebody
else. If you hit them in a way that actually causes damage,
rather than being punished by lashes which a normal transgression would be
punished by, it's punished by compensation. But ironically when the damage is
trivial, it's less than a פרוטה's prutah worth, because there's no compensation
to be made, it's actually punishable by lashes. All right, so I
went now and I hit this guy. The better answer I would
have said could have been that I hit him in a way
that there was no בשת boshet and that there was no צער.
tza'ar. But it doesn't sound like there was no בשת, boshet, right?
Because it says you're cursing and you're screaming and whatever, you're doing
all these things. Seems like there's embarrassment. So the גמרא Gemara says
fine. We're talking about getting lashes, we're not talking about being exempt
for payment. Payment maybe is made, whatever for the embarrassment. But we're
talking about whether getting lashes for the actual act of hitting when
the hitting caused less than a פרוטה's prutah worth of damage. So
why shouldn't I? So who cares he's about to be executed, I
just did a prohibition, right? I hit somebody. Why should I be
and if there's no payment then I should get lashes, why should
I be exempt? So the גמרא Gemara says
ואמר רבי אמי אמר רבי יוחנן כל הכה שאין בה שוה פרוטה
לוקה. Ve'amar Rabbi Ami Amar Rabbi Yochanan: Kol hakah she'ein bah shaveh
prutah lokeh. You get lashes. Okay, so therefore so why not get
lashes? So the גמרא Gemara says no.
מאי פטור דקאמר פטור מממון. Mai patur dekamar patur mimamon. You're exempt
from monetary payment. So then what does it have to do with
the fact that the guy is being taken out to be executed?
All you're telling me is that if somebody hits somebody and it's
not a penny's worth of damage, he doesn't pay any money. Well
first of all duh, of course he doesn't pay any money if
it's not a penny's worth of damage, right? And פטור patur doesn't
sound like you're just exempt from money, it sounds like you're totally
exempt. It's a very bizarre read. It seems like it's funny רש"י
Rashi doesn't even bother explaining this, but it seems like what the
גמרא Gemara is getting at is the point I made before which
is look, בשת boshet and צער tza'ar maybe you do pay. But
you're not going to pay for physical injury because somebody who's about
to be executed, again I'm reading this into the גמרא Gemara I
don't know if that's what the גמרא's Gemara saying. But somebody who's
about to be executed, there's no value to their person, like you
know to their to their arm, to their leg or whatever, right?
In terms of physical injury. So yes, the גמרא Gemara continues maybe
you will pay בשת boshet and צער, tza'ar, but you're not going
to pay any the cost of נזק, nezek, of physical damage. Okay,
and yes, would you get lashes? Maybe you would get lashes but
that's not our interest. So since the guy's going to get executed,
you're not going to pay any monetary value for the physical damage.
For the בשת boshet and צער tza'ar maybe you would but not
for the physical damage.
Yeah and inherently any נזק nezek is not equal to a פרוטה
prutah because exactly.
I don't know if that's what the גמרא's Gemara saying but at
least otherwise it doesn't make any sense to read that into this
case. So it's like my case about the pot that's been dropped
off the roof which you damage on the way down. So okay,
בשת boshet we admit it and צער tza'ar we didn't discuss but
let's admit that. Fine, maybe there is בשת boshet and צער. tza'ar.
But there won't be נזק. nezek. That's what you're פטור patur for.
Okay, but now we get back to the question of the son.
So then why is the son חייב? chayav? Okay, So גמרא Gemara
says,
so דקאמר d'kamar פטור ממון, patur mamon, מכלל mikhlal דבנו d'bno חייב
chayav בממון? b'mamon? So one minute. So then it would sound like
the son is חייב chayav if you're saying the point is to
say that a third person who hits this person is exempt from
monetary payment, even if he'll get lashes, even if he'll get lashes.
Okay, so and the son is חייב. chayav. So the son is
חייב chayav sounds like the son has to pay monetary. Like it's
one thing to say the son is חייב chayav for hitting a
father, but why is he paying monetary if the person has no
value? Okay, so גמרא Gemara says בנו חייב בממון? b'no chayav b'mamon?
אלא בדינו, ella b'dino, הכא נמי בדינו. hacha nami b'dino.
So if the son is חייב, chayav, it must mean the son
is חייב chayav for מיתה misa for hitting the father. So when
you say this guy is חייב, chayav, this guy is פטור, patur,
the third person, it must mean פטור patur not just in monetary
payment, it must mean פטור patur in what the normal punishment would
be, מלקות. malkus. But why should he be פטור patur in מלקות?
malkus? So it doesn't make any sense, meaning, to say there's no
monetary payments here and the son is still חייב מיתה, chayav misa,
that could make sense. This person who's being executed has no value,
so there's no monetary payments, but the son is חייב מיתה chayav
misa because he still hit a father. But then the other guy
should be חייב מלקות. chayav malkus. So the phrasing doesn't make sense.
It sounds like one guy, the son is פטור, patur, you know,
like
if—if you're saying that guy is פטור, patur, it should sound like
he's פטור patur completely, not just פטור patur in ממון. mamon. So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
אלא, ella, where were we? So far pretty good answer. But okay,
אלא, ella, the גמרא Gemara says אחר היינו טעמא דפטור דאמר קרא
achar haynu ta'ama d'patur d'amar k'ra ונשיא בעמך לא תאור v'nasi b'amcha
lo sa'or בעושה מעשה עמך. b'oseh ma'aseh amcha. Do not curse a
נשיא nasi in your nation, and from that we learn a general
prohibition to curse anybody. And by the way, right until now we've
also only been talking about hitting. We haven't dealt with the cursing
problem. So now we're going to deal with both problems. This person
who is חייב מיתה, chayav misa, there is no longer a prohibition
against cursing and hitting them. Forget the monetary issues, whether there's monetary
payments they will or they won't be made, fine, that's not our
issue. Our issue is do you do a—do you transgress a prohibition
by cursing and hitting them. And since this person is no longer
עושה מעשה עמך, oseh ma'aseh amcha, right, he's basically he's no longer
acting like a fellow Jew, so this person loses the protection of
the law in many areas. Okay, that's a very interesting question. What
types of sins does a person do that means that they're no
longer protected by certain interpersonal laws? Okay, and there's different הלכות halachas
in different cases. Can you lend somebody who's a מחלל שבת mechallel
Shabbos etc., can you lend them money with ריבית? ribbis? Right, do
you have to—when do you have to return an אבידה? aveida? Can
you overcharge somebody? Like how does it get measured whether they're עושה
מעשה עמך oseh ma'aseh amcha or not? Now this person isn't just
somebody who does עבירות, aveiras, right, they're—you know,
this is somebody who actually is about to be executed. So there's
one question about what הלכות halachas does this apply to, and then
there's another question about how severe does a person's transgressions have to
be to put him in this category of אינו עושה מעשה עמך,
eino oseh ma'aseh amcha, not acting like a fellow Jew, okay? But
once a person is in that category, for this הלכה halacha of
cursing—and we're going to assume the same is true about hitting—they are
no longer protected and you no longer transgress. So maybe you might
have to pay compensation, that's not our issue. Maybe yes, maybe no.
But the point is a normal person who curses or hits somebody
who's about to be executed for a sin is no longer transgressing.
And that's why the other person is exempt. So then the question
is, so then it would seem though by a son and a
father—and you could sort of understand this—you know, that's not just about
the fact that you're a fellow Jew and deserve, you know, protection
and respect and whatever. You know, the parental bond, you know, maybe
transcends all of that and remains prohibited even in those cases. Let's
see what it says. Okay. So it says בעושה מעשה עמך, v'oseh
ma'aseh amcha, הא תינח קללה, ha tenach klala, fine, that's why he's
exempt by cursing. הכאה מנלן? haka minalan? How do you know about
הכאה? hakaah? דאקיש הכאה לקללה. d'akish hakaah l'klala. We link the two.
It's not exactly clear how we link the two, it doesn't exactly
quote a verse, but logically we link the two. They're either a
verbal or a physical onslaught of the person and therefore it only
applies when the person is a עושה מעשה עמך, oseh ma'aseh amcha,
not about to be executed for a sin, not completely considered to
be on the outside of society. אי הכי בנו נמי. ei hachi
b'no nami. So then how would we assume that the child is
different? Maybe the child also should only be prohibited in those cases?
So כדאמר רב פנחס kid'amar Rav Pinchas בשעשה תשובה, b'she'asah teshuvah, הכא
נמי בשעשה תשובה. hacha nami b'she'asah teshuvah. So funny, the גמרא Gemara
keeps on going back and forth. No, רב פנחס Rav Pinchas says
in another case that after he's done תשובה, teshuvah, he goes back
to be considered a good fellow Jew. So here too that's why
the son is prohibited because the father did תשובה. teshuvah. Of course,
if the father did תשובה, teshuvah, you're back to the first question.
Why is it okay for the other person to hit him, right?
Anytime we try to fix the son problem, we create the problem,
you know, like you've got to come up with
a reason that distinguishes between the son and somebody else, not just
this global answer. אי הכי אחר נמי. ei hachi acher nami. Okay,
so obviously—so then if the guy did תשובה, teshuvah, then you're back
to why it's okay for the other guy. So no, that's not
a good answer. You have to come up with an explanation why
it's okay for the other person and not okay for the son.
So אמר רב מרי amar Rav Mari בעמך במקוים שבעמך. b'amcha b'mekuyam
she'b'amcha. So now, it's somebody who is, so we're going back to
עושה מעשה עמך, oseh ma'aseh amcha, but we're explaining it more narrowly,
like as I said. A, you have to decide which areas of
הלכה halacha does the idea of עושה מעשה עמך oseh ma'aseh amcha
apply? Is it that the person is only, my obligation to the
other person is only if they're doing like, you know, considered to
be like upstanding citizen. The other question is what puts you on
the outside? How big of a sin? So אינו עושה מעשה עמך
eino oseh ma'aseh amcha could be applied to somebody who's just, I
don't know, not observant, he's מחלל שבת, mechallel Shabbos, you know, whatever
he does. Okay, doesn't keep כשרות. kashrus. This is a much narrower
definition. It's the same idea but a much narrower definition.
במקיים שבעמך. bimkayem shebe'amcha. Somebody who still has a right to be
alive. If you look at רש"י, Rashi, במקיים הראוי להתקיים בלא זה
שנגמר דינו. bimkayem haraui lehiskayem belo zeh shenigmar dino. So it's not
just not observant, but they've lost their legal right to be alive.
They're about to be executed. That's a very narrow category. And that
type of a person you don't have a prohibition against hitting them
or cursing them. Fine, but then we're back to the son. Why
is the son prohibited? Okay, אי הכי בנו נמי. ei hachi beno
nami. So going back and forth. So מדי midi we're finally, thank
God, look like we're coming for a landing, right? מדי דהוה לאחר
מיתה. midi dehavah le'achar misah. Ah, since we just said that it's
not just about אינו עושה מעשה עמך, eino oseh ma'aseh amcha, not
just that they did a terrible sin, but it's like they no
longer are have a right to be alive and deserve to be
alive, meaning what? It's like they're dead. So now the category under
which we're exempting a person for cursing them or hitting them is
not because, oh, he's not an upstanding citizen. The reason that they've
exempted is it's like he's already dead because he deserves to be
executed. So if I went ahead and I cursed somebody who was
already dead or I hit somebody in the grave, I wouldn't have
transgressed anything. But a son who curses his father after death, we're
about to learn in the next משנה, mishnah, the איסור issur of
cursing applies after death. So the exemption here is that it's like
the guy is dead. That works to exempt a normal person, but
it doesn't work to exempt a son. So now the question is,
but רש"י Rashi says one minute, let's just take a look at
the next משנה. mishnah. המכה אביו
ואמו אינו חייב עד שיעשה בה חבורה. hamakeh aviv ve'imo eino chayav
ad sheya'aseh bah chaburah. So you have to make a wound, which
is what we've been dealing with. זה חומר במקלל מבמכה שהמקלל לאחר
מיתה חייב והמכה לאחר מיתה פטור. zeh chomer bimekallel mibemakeh shehamkallel le'achar
misah chayav vehamakeh le'achar misah patur. If you curse after death you're
חייב, chayav, if you hit you're פטור. patur. So now that we
said it's like this guy is dead, we understand
why the son is חייב chayav for cursing, but why is the
son חייב chayav for hitting? The next משנה mishnah says that hitting
after death is exempt, right? So רש"י Rashi says here's the reason.
Hitting after death by a father should also be חייב. chayav. The
only reason hitting after death by a father is not חייב chayav
or a mother is because, definition of hitting remember
is חבורה, chaburah, making a wound, taking out blood. Blood represents נפש,
nefesh, the life, the life force. After the person is dead, the
blood no longer represents the life force. So this person, technically you
would be חייב chayav for חבורה chaburah after death if you could
have a case of חבורה chaburah where it took out living blood
as it were. Okay, so where do you have that case? This
guy who's about to be executed. Technically it's like he's already dead,
but the חבורה chaburah is also a חבורה chaburah because biologically, physiologically
you still are taking out blood and making a wound, right, you
could make a wound in a body after death too, but here
the point is you're taking out blood that is still pumping. Okay,
so therefore that's what we say. We've now explained it. How we
have this case that's a normal person who curses this guy who's
about to or hits guy who's about to be killed is exempt
and the son is חייב. chayav. One way of explaining it is
that they're trying to drag him out and execute him and he's
refusing. And the difference is that the son doesn't operate as an
agent for the court in these cases, which answers our question. Can
the son operate as an agent of the court to hit or
curse a father and according to that the answer would be no.
The other point has nothing to do with it. It's just the
fact that this person now because of the death penalty, it's like
he's dead in certain ways. So that means for somebody else to
hit him or curse him would not transgress, whereas for a son
even after death these prohibitions apply, and even hitting the father, he's
חייב chayav because it still causes the wound, even to the degree
that you consider the father to be as if he's already dead.
Let's read that in רש"י. Rashi. מדי דהוה לאחר מיתה. midi dehavah
le'achar misah. רש"י Rashi says יליפנא לקמן מקלל לאחר מיתה חייב. yalifna
lekaman mekallel le'achar misah chayav. ואם תאמר והתנן מכה לאחר מיתה פטור.
ve'im tomar vehatnan makeh le'achar misah patur. Okay, if it's like he's
dead and you're חייב chayav for cursing, why are you חייב chayav
for hitting? והכא מחייב ליה הכאה דקתני היכהו וקיללו. ve'hacha mechayev leh
haka'ah dektani hika'u vekillelo. היינו טעמא דפטור מכה לאחר מיתה משום דבעינן
חבורה. hainu ta'ama depatur makeh le'achar misah mishum debe'inan chaburah. The only
reason somebody who hits a father is exempt after death is it's
not really considered a wound. ולאחר מיתה ליכא חבורה דליכא נפש דנפקא
ליה על ידי נפש. ule'achar misah leika chaburah deleika nefesh denafka leh
al yedei nefesh. Okay, so again it's not that it doesn't physically
make a wound but it's not a meaningful one because it's not
taking some of the life blood like out of the body cause
the guy's already dead. והיוצא ליהרג אית ביה חבורה דחיי הוא אלא
דסופו למות. ve'hayotzei leihareg it beh chaburah dechai hu ela desofo lamus.
We're not saying he's really dead, we're saying he's... about to die.
So therefore for him, somebody who's about to die, a normal person
doesn't have a prohibition against hitting or wounding, against hitting or cursing
them. A son does have a prohibition against hitting or cursing a
father or a mother who is about to die, and that's why
it still applies to the son, and that is the difference. Let's
just finish up and then I'll take your question, Jenna. אמר רבה
בר רב הונא וכן תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל לכל אין הבן נעשה
שליח לאביו להכותו ולקללו.
Amar Rabba bar
Rav Huna vechen tana d'bei Rabbi Yishmael lechol ein haben na’aseh shaliach
l’aviv l’hako’oto ul’kal’lo. So now we're answering our question: a son cannot
be, either is not, or even if he is, I'm saying won't
be meaningful for him to be assigned that role of being a
agent of the court to hit or to curse a father, חוץ
ממסית, chutz m'meisit, שהרי אמרה תורה לא תחמול ולא תכסה עליו, sheharei
amra Torah lo tachmol velo techaseh alav, don't have any compassion, so
even a son can be sort of playing that role. So now
that says that actually if therefore there is a case where a
son is considered to be a legitimate agent of the court, then
he actually will be exempt. It's just that in most cases, the
son would never be a legitimate agent of the court in that
role. Yes, Jenna, you had a question?
Sorry, I just, you said
מסית meisit is what?
What? What are you asking me? מסית? Meisit? מסית, Meisit, מסית meisit
is the person who is like seducing others to commit idolatry, right?
That person we are extra, like we don't give them התראה, hatra'ah,
we don't give them warning, right? So here too, since there's such
this mandate to get rid of them, to destroy, you know, to
execute them, it would extend even to allowing the son to play
that role.
Okay, and then my other question was, we already did the גברא
קטילא? gavra katila?
Yeah, but before we were doing it to say, so the difference
is is that before we were doing it to say that you're
exempt from monetary payment, because it's like again like the pot that's
flying off of the rooftop. And now we're doing it to say
that it gets you out of the prohibition, the transgression, because since
that transgression is בנשיא בעמך, b'nasi b'amecha, it only applies to somebody
who is alive, not somebody who's dead, right? If I cursed somebody
who's dead, I wouldn't transgress, and it doesn't apply to somebody who's
about to be executed. So it's specifically about the transgression, which then
sort of and then that allows us to make that distinction between
the son, because the son is prohibited against cursing a dead parent,
and according to Rashi, and cursing a live parent who's about to
die, again, that would not be a normal person, but that would
be for a child, for a son or daughter.
And like nowadays, like you could be condemned to die, there could
be like 15 years between the time of the...
Right, right, and right in the גמרא Gemara it was much quicker.
Right, which
is also explains why right, that's a good point too, it's a
small category, it also explains why that defines the person's like legal
status so much, because the amount of time would be very short.
Right. Okay, so let's go on. By the way, I should just
say parenthetically because it's very important, this issue about עושה מעשה עמך
oseh ma’aseh amcha and how much that impacts, not the question about
liable to death penalty, but how much being a like an upstanding
observant Jew or whatever impacts the child-parent relationship. You know, there's like
a הלכה halacha that a child is not supposed to sit שבעה
shiva for a parent who's a רשע, rasha, and you read some
of these books like, you know, like I don't know, like I
think in the Artscroll Laws of Mourning, which in general is an
excellent book, I mean it has all, you know, it's extremely detailed
or whatever, and I but I think anyway, you look at there
it says, well, if the parent wasn't a שומר שבת, shomer Shabbos,
then the child shouldn't be sitting שבעה. shiva. Like what? Like you
know, that they're using that category of רשע rasha nowadays, I mean
you know, nobody ever heard about תינוק שנשבה, tinok shenishba, like and
you know, there's a redefinition of that category. But it does become
an interesting question about abusive relationships, right? And how much does, you
know, the idea of כיבוד אב ואם, kibbud av v’em, you know,
sort of create obligations even in the context of an abusive type
of a relationship. Now that's not the case here, because that's specifically
about the dynamics between parent and child, it's not that the parent
in general was a bad person. Right. But how much, as my
general approach to that, not to digress, which I'm already am, but
it just seems to me very relevant to this issue about like
how one relates to the parent and the respect based on the
type of person the parent is. So some people want to say
you don't have to do like, you know, שבעה shiva or כיבוד
אב ואם kibbud av v’em or whatever if it's abusive because the
parent is a רשע. rasha. Now I admit there are people out
there that are רשעים, reshaim, but to me I don't think that
that's the most direct way of addressing it, and it's like pretty
harsh to all of a sudden decide that just, you know, that
we're going to decide that this person is a רשע rasha in
this sort of absolute way. To me, the answer is much clearer
that all of these בין אדם לחבירו bein adam l’chaveiro type of
things, including כיבוד אב ואם, kibbud av v’em, the general governing principle
is like חייך וחיי חבירך חייך קודמין, chayecha vechayei chaveirecha chayecha kodmin,
that you have a prior responsibility to yourself. And even for example
in honoring parents, like everybody knows the story about how the what
do you call it, you know, the the mother comes and tears
the garments off of the rabbi and spits on him in public
and he doesn't say anything and so on, which seems like you
have to be willing to endure a lot of personal shame and
suffering for honoring parents. But the פוסקים poskim say that that's only
after the fact he didn't react, but to protect himself from being
in... embarrassed or even protect himself from monetary loss, he would have
been allowed
to have stopped his parent even if it would require having embarrassed
his
parent, he is allowed to protect yourself before your obligation for כיבוד
אב ואם. Kibbud Av v'Em. So I think that that's the real
way to operate in those situations is to understand that the prior
obligation even in parental relationships, the first obligation is to yourself. So
anyway, this seems to me very relevant for discussing about the parental,
the obligation to a parent here who might be a רשע Rasha
in other ways and
חייב מיתה, Chayav Mita, you have these limits of direct defense, right,
about הכאה Haka'ah and קללה Kelalah and so on, and but what
about also cases about כיבוד Kibbud and other types of issues? Okay,
so let's take a look now at the next משנה, Mishna, which
is a continuation of what we've been
discussing. We've already addressed multiple parts of it. Okay, המכה אביו ואמו
אינו חייב עד שיעשה בהם חבורה. HaMakeh aviv v'imo eino chayav ad
she-ya'aseh bahem chaburah. זה חומר במקלל מבמכה. Ze chomer b'mekalel mi-b'makeh. So
first of all you have to do a wound which we discussed.
זה חומר במקלל מבמכה. Ze chomer b'mekalel mi-b'makeh. שהמקלל לאחר מיתה חייב.
She-ha-mekalel l'achar mita chayav. Cursing after death you're חייב. chayav. והמכה לאחר
מיתה פטור. Ve-ha-makeh l'achar mita patur. Hitting after death you're exempt as
רש״י Rashi says 'cause it's not really considered a wound. תנו רבנן.
Tanu rabanan. אביו ואמו קלל. Aviv v'imo killel. So it says he's
cursed his father or mother, it says so he has to be
put to death. ולאחר מיתה. Ve-l'achar mita. So the extra repetition of
אביו ואמו קלל. aviv v'imo killel. What's the whole פסוק? pasuk? Where
does it appear? ויקרא Vayikra nineteen what?
Does anybody have that?
פרק כ פסוק ט. Perek Kaf Pasuk Tet.
כי איש איש אשר
יקלל את אביו ואת אמו מות יומת אביו ואמו קלל דמיו בו.
Ki ish ish
asher
yekalel et aviv v'et imo
mot yumat aviv v'imo killel damav bo. Okay, so he shall be
put to death. Now, ודמיו בו ve-damav bo again, because now we're
dealing with קללה. kelalah. קללה Kelalah you might remember is ודמיו בו
ve-damav bo is סקילה. sekilah. Okay, so right? הכאה Haka'ah is חנק,
chenek, but קללה kelalah is סקילה. sekilah. So it's a little repetitious,
right? It says איש איש. ish ish. What's the פסוק pasuk again?
אשר יקלל
את אביו ואת אמו מות
יומת.
Asher yekalel et aviv v'et imo mot
yumat.
כי
איש
איש אשר יקלל את
אביו ואת אמו מות יומת
אביו ואמו קלל.
Ki ish ish asher yekalel et aviv v'et imo
mot yumat
aviv v'imo killel. So we understand what ודמיו בו ve-damav bo is
telling us, which is סקילה sekilah by קללה. kelalah. But why do
you need to repeat אביו ואמו קלל? aviv v'imo killel? That's a
little redundant. So that's telling us to broaden the scope even לאחר
מיתה. l'achar mita. Okay. אביו ואמו קלל לאחר מיתה. Aviv v'imo killel
l'achar mita. שיכול הוא בחייב במכה וחייב במקלל. She-yachol hu b'chayav b'makeh
v'chayav b'mekalel. מה במכה אינו חייב אלא מחיים. Mah b'makeh eino chayav
ela mechayim. In the same way hitting is only in life. How
do we know that? Just by intuitively. Like to hit somebody
means that they are somehow alive, also 'cause you're hitting their body,
their live body. When you curse them, you don't need a physical
body in front of you. So the same way, right, there's an
implicit, right, you implicitly understand, right, why קללה kelalah is more relevant
after death 'cause קללה kelalah never needed the person to be physically
present when you did the קללה. kelalah. Okay. מה במכה אינו חייב
אלא מחיים. Mah b'makeh eino chayav ela mechayim. אף מקלל אינו חייב
אלא מחיים. Af mekalel eino chayav ela mechayim. Maybe cursing is also
only when it's
alive. תלמוד לומר. Talmud lomar. And now we're getting back to the
נשיא בעמך Nasi b'amcha issue we dealt with before. Right, remember that
פסוק pasuk נשיא בעמך לא תאור Nasi b'amcha lo ta'or was about
cursing. So this ברייתא braita is assuming against the גמרא Gemara we
said earlier that the limitation to that they have to be בעמך,
b'amcha, right, is limited to cursing, would not apply to hitting. Hitting
would not matter whether they were considered to be an upstanding citizen
or not. Okay. So when it comes to
cursing, מה במכה שעשה בו שלא בעמך כבעמך. Mah b'makeh she'asah bo
shelo b'amcha k'v'amcha. It doesn't matter whether they're an upstanding citizen or
not. You're always חייב chayav for hitting. לא חיו בו לאחר מיתה.
Lo chiyu bo l'achar mita. So even though hitting is broader, it
includes even a non-upstanding citizen and nevertheless it doesn't apply after death.
מקלל שלא עשה בו שלא בעמך כבעמך. Mekalel shelo asah bo shelo
b'amcha k'v'amcha. By cursing where it only applies to an upstanding citizen,
אינו דין שלא חיו בו לאחר מיתה? eino din shelo chiyu bo
l'achar mita? So if it's narrower already to begin with cursing, maybe
it also should not apply after death. תלמוד לומר. Talmud lomar. So
this is interesting, this distinction of בעמך b'amcha which we'll get back
to, we've dealt with before. But let's now focus on the death
issue, the after death. תלמוד לומר אביו ואמו קלל Talmud lomar aviv
v'imo killel לאחר מיתה. l'achar mita. The extra אביו ואמו קלל aviv
v'imo killel says even after death. Fine. Now the גמרא Gemara says
one minute, to say that that extra verse applies even after death
by cursing, הניחא לרבי יונתן henicha l'Rabbi Yonatan דמייתר ליה קרא אביו
ואמו קלל d'miyatar lei kra aviv v'imo killel that the plus פסוק
pasuk is extra. אלא לרבי יאשיה מאי איכא למימר? Ela l'Rabbi Yoshiyah
mai ika l'meimar? For Rabbi Yoshiyah that verse is not extra. Why
not? דתניא איש איש. D'tanya ish ish. This is our פסוק pasuk
איש איש. ish ish. Okay. מה תלמוד לומר איש איש? Mah talmud
lomar ish ish? לרבות בת טומטום ואנדרוגינוס. L'rabot bat tumtum v'androgynos. So
it's not only if it just said איש ish it would only
have been a man. איש איש Ish ish tells you daughter, טומטום,
tumtum, and אנדרוגינוס. androgynos. Even a woman or a טומטום tumtum and
אנדרוגינוס. androgynos. Okay, all of those, whoever the perpetrator is, is going
to be חייב. chayav. Okay, איש איש ish ish לרבות בת, טומטום
ואנדרוגינוס. lerabot bat tumtum ve'androgynos. אשר יקלל את אביו ואמו, asher yekalel
et aviv ve'imo, אין לי אלא אביו ואמו, en li ela aviv
ve'imo, maybe means you have to curse both mother and father together.
אביו שלא אמו אמו שלא אביו מנין? aviv shelo imo, imo shelo
aviv minayin? How do you know even one? תלמוד לומר talmud lomar
אביו ואמו קלל, aviv ve'imo kilel, אביו קלל אמו קלל. aviv kilel,
imo kilel. דברי רבי אושיא. divrei Rabbi Oshaya. Rabbi Oshaya says that's
why it repeats it. And the way it repeats it is because
if it would have just said את אביו ואמו, et aviv ve'imo,
you would have said you have to curse both of them. But
because it repeats it, we get to read it this way: יקלל
את אביו, yekalel et aviv, so אביו aviv is enough. And here
it says אמו קלל, imo kilel, so mother is enough. What's both?
It repeats it, but the verb here is close to אביו aviv
and the verb here is close to אמו imo tells you either
one is enough. So the repetition is not to tell you לאחר
מיתה, le'achar misa, the repetition is to tell you either one is
enough. That's what רבי אושיא Rabbi Oshaya says. רבי יונתן Rabbi Yonatan
אומר omer משמע שם כאחד ומשמע אחד ואחד בפני עצמו. mashma shem
ke'echad umashma echad ve'echad bifne atzmo. No, when it says a ו,
vav, it could either mean both together or it could mean A
or B. עד שיפרט לך הכתוב יחדיו, ad sheyefaret lecha hakatuv yachdav,
unless it says together like בשור ובחמור יחדיו. bishor vechamor yachdav. Okay?
Or כלאים, kilayim, you know, צמר ופשתים יחדיו. tzemer ufishtim yachdav. Together
means you need both of them. Without the יחדיו yachdav it means
either. So according to רבי אושיא Rabbi Oshaya though that you need
this to tell me either, where do you know לאחר מיתה? le'achar
misa? So the גמרא Gemara says מנא ליה? mana lei? Where does
רבי אושיא Rabbi Oshaya know לאחר מיתה? le'achar misa? נפקא ליה nafka
lei מומקלל אביו ואמו מות יומת. miumekalel aviv ve'imo mot yumat. The
פסוק pasuk by in not in ויקרא, Vayikra, but in שמות. Shemot.
It says again מקלל אביו ואמו מות יומת. mekalel aviv ve'imo mot
yumat. That's an extra פסוק. pasuk. Right? We already know from here
you're put to death. So what's it saying there? Even after מיתה.
misa. ואידך? ve'idach? Now, if you learn after מיתה misa from this,
what do you do by the פסוק pasuk in שמות? Shemot? אה,
oh, מיבעי ליה mibaya lei לרבות lerabot בת טומטום ואנדרוגינוס. bat tumtum
ve'androgynos. Okay, to tell you בת טומטום ואנדרוגינוס. bat tumtum ve'androgynos? Now
what do we mean בת bat, טומטום tumtum ואנדרוגינוס? ve'androgynos. Because there,
there's no description of the subject. It just says ומקלל אביו ואמו
מות יומת. umekalel aviv ve'imo mot yumat. So it doesn't matter whether
the one who does it is a man or a woman or
whoever. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says ותיפוק ליה veteipokei lei מאיש
איש? mei'ish ish? But we already learned that from the איש איש.
ish ish. No, דברה תורה כלשון בני אדם. dibra Torah kilshon bnei
adam. Oh, that's just, that doesn't mean anything. That's just, you know,
a normal way of speaking. Okay, so now we've figured out the
economy of the verses. Everybody learns from one verse or another the
idea that it doesn't matter who the perpetrator is and that it
applies even לאחר מיתה. le'achar misa. Now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: וליתני ulisni חומר במכה מבמקלל, chomer bamake mibamekalel, שהמכה עשה בו
שלא בעמך כבעמך. shemake asah bo shelo beamcha kiveamcha. Now, in passing
in this ברייתא, braita, we learned that this issue about upstanding citizen,
are you חייב chayav if you curse or hit a father or
a mother who's not an עושה מעשה עמך, ose maaseh amcha, a
non-upstanding halakhic citizen? So this ברייתא braita in passing said you're exempt
by cursing because it's ונשיא בעמך לא תאור. venasi beamcha lo ta'or.
That the general פסוק pasuk against cursing, which also applies to parents,
right, is בעמך, beamcha, in your nation. So that does not apply
to cursing another Jew who's not an upstanding citizen, and it doesn't
and also even a parent who's not an upstanding citizen, you're exempt.
Okay? So why don't we say in our משנה, Mishnah, right? Because
that's the פסוק, pasuk, right? Remember. The פסוק pasuk we learned that
it's prohibited to curse a parent or to hit a parent is
the same that we learned that it's אסור assur to hit or
curse a normal Jew, right? By hitting הכאה haka'ah לא יוסיף להכותו,
lo yosif lehakoto, right, which is about anybody who's getting מלקות, malkos,
לא יוסיף להכותו, lo yosif lehakoto, and by cursing it's ונשיא בעמך
לא תאור. venasi beamcha lo ta'or. Okay, and those are general פסוקים
pesukim that you're not allowed to hit or curse another Jew, but
also the parent. Well here it says בעמך. beamcha. So we're going
to say that the prohibition of cursing a normal Jew and a
parent is only when they're an upstanding halakhic citizen, whereas hitting would
apply regardless. So why didn't our משנה Mishnah give that as a
distinct, the same way it's giving a difference between whether it applies
after death, it should have given this as a difference between hitting
and cursing. Okay, so that's the גמרא's Gemara question. וליתני ulisni why
didn't our משנה Mishnah say חומר במכה מבמקלל chomer bamake mibamekalel that
hitting is in a way a broader scope than cursing? Cursing is
broader that it applies after death, but hitting is broader in the
following way: שהמכה עשה בו שלא בעמך כבעמך. shemake asah bo shelo
beamcha kiveamcha. Hitting applies whether the person's an upstanding citizen or not.
מה שאין כן mah sheken במקלל bamekalel as opposed to cursing. קסבר,
kasavar, no, because the author of our משנה Mishnah holds מקישינן הכאה
לקללה, makshinan haka'ah liklala, that we link the two, that actually the
same way cursing is limited to עושה מעשה עמך, ose maaseh amcha,
hitting is also limited to עושה מעשה עמך. ose maaseh amcha. So
I just want to pause for a moment, right, because the discussion
a minute ago before we got to this next משנה, Mishnah, when
the guy was being taken out to be executed, if you remember,
it only excluded him because he was about to be executed. executed,
because he was no longer like מקויים. mekuyam. He no longer had
a lease on life. Now we're going back to actually exclude people
on the basis that they're not observant, whatever observant means, עושה מעשה
עמך, oseh ma'aseh amcha, a certain degree of violation that they're considered
to be on the outs. Okay, not just about to be executed.
Everybody agrees that that exempts you from cursing, and the question is
does it even exempt you from hitting? Okay, so that's really interesting,
right? How much does that now loosen those whole prohibitions, right, to
go ahead and to take a thorn out of your father's toe
and might cause blood, that would be a חייב מיתה. chayav mita.
But if the father is not שומר מצוות, shomer mitzvot, then all
of a sudden it stops being prohibited, right? So alright, so let's
just finish it. So our תנא tanna holds that they're both permitted
in that case. מקישין הכאה לקללה. makkishin hakah lekellalah. So now the
גמרא gemara just ends with the following words: לימא הני תנאי כי
הני תנאי, leima hanei tanna'ei ki hanei tanna'ei, let's say this debate
of תנאים, tanna'im, which is does, are you exempt when the person
is not observant or עושה מעשה עמך oseh ma'aseh amcha in hitting,
does that exempt you, it parallels this debate. דתניא חדא, detanya chada,
one ברייתא braita teaches: כותי אתה מצווה על הכאתו ואי אתה מצווה
על קללתו. Kuti atah metzuveh al haka'ato ve'ei atah metzuveh al kilelato.
A Samaritan, you are prohibited against hitting, but not against cursing. So
what's the difference between cursing and hitting? Presumably it's exactly this: a
Samaritan is considered Jewish but not basically observant, doesn't follow rabbinic law.
So they're not עושה מעשה עמך. oseh ma'aseh amcha. By the way,
עושה מעשה עמך oseh ma'aseh amcha works very well here, right, because
here the lack of observance really is not just they're not observant,
they follow a different laws of observance because they're part of a
different type of group, they're not part of the rabbinic group. So
it really isn't עושה מעשה עמך, oseh ma'aseh amcha, right, it really
is about a different type of a group or national identity. Anyway,
so therefore you're still, you're exempt for cursing, but you're still liable
for hitting. דתניא אידך, detanya idach, we've got another ברייתא: braita: אי
אתה מצווה לא על קללתו ולא על הכאתו, ee atah metzuveh lo
al kilelato velo al haka'ato, you're exempt for both. So סברוה, savruah,
we assumed דכולי עלמא כותים גירי אמת הן, dekulei alma kutim geirei
emet hein, everybody holds that they're legally Jewish, that it was a
good conversion. מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי, mai lav beha kamiflegi, let's say
this is the debate. דמר סבר מקישין הכאה לקללה, demar savar makkishin
hakah lekellalah, one says that actually they're linked, so since we all
agree you're exempt for cursing because they're not עושה מעשה עמך, oseh
ma'aseh amcha, so one holds you're also exempt for hitting because it's
linked, you're exempt for both. ומר סבר לא מקישין הכאה לקללה, umar
savar lo makkishin hakah lekellalah, no, you're only exempt for cursing, not
for hitting. So that's a nice way to read that debate. ואמרת
לא, ve'amrat lo, not necessarily. דכולי עלמא לא מקישין הכאה לקללה, dekulei
alma lo makkishin hakah lekellalah, everybody could agree we don't link them,
that when somebody is not עושה מעשה עמך, oseh ma'aseh amcha, you're
exempt from cursing, you're not exempt from hitting. By the way, you
do understand the logic for that, right, that if somebody is seen
as not, you know, keeping up to the standards of the people,
maybe to curse the person actually serves, you know, the public good.
Like it's a way of us saying this person is horrific, nobody
should follow him, he's blah blah blah, you know, and you curse
the person out. Hitting somebody is still physical, the reality of physical
injury, right, even if somebody is not observant, it doesn't give you
a license to inflict physical injury on a person. Okay, so the
גמרא gemara says everybody agrees to that distinction. It only gives you
a license to curse or means it's not prohibited to curse, it
remains prohibited to hit. So what's the issue? והכא בהא קמיפלגי, vehacha
beha kamiflegi, מר סבר כותים גירי אמת הן, mar savar kutim geirei
emet hein, that they are Jewish. So if they're Jewish, you're allowed
to curse them because they're not עושה מעשה עמך, oseh ma'aseh amcha,
but you're not allowed to hit them. That's exactly that distinction. ומר
סבר כותים גירי אריות הן, umar savar kutim geirei arayot hein, they're
not Jewish and therefore the prohibition doesn't apply in either category. אי
הכי, ee hachi, says the גמרא, gemara, no no, that can't be,
because היינו דקתני עלה שור כישראל, hainu dekatni alah shor keyisrael, but
the end of the ברייתא braita says whether you are or are
not allowed to hit them, you know, their ox is like a
Jewish ox. Which means what? If a non-Jewish ox gores a Jewish
ox, it pays full. If a Jewish ox gores a non-Jewish ox,
it's totally exempt. And that's this very difficult משנה בבבא קמא, mishna
bevava kamma, the גמרא gemara has a whole discussion, right, that that
certainly, you know, shows very unfair application of the law, has a
whole discussion there. Okay, but if it's but here, their ox is
treated like a Jewish ox. You know, if it's if it's a
first few times it's half payment, if it's three times it's full
payment. Anyway, that הלכה halacha that for damages of their animals, it's
considered like a Jewish animal, clear that we treat them as Jewish,
that we're seeing them as Jews, not as non-Jews. So you see
that both of these assume that they're Jews. And nevertheless, one says
you're exempt even when you hit them. Okay? So therefore, אלא שמע
מינה בהיקשא פליגי
שמע מינה. ela shema
mina behekisha pileigi
shema mina. So you see that
both of these ברייתות braitot assume they're Jews, and the distinction is
one ברייתא braita says okay, they're Jewish, but they're not עושה מעשה
עמך, oseh ma'aseh amcha, so therefore you're allowed, you're prohibited to hit,
but you are not prohibited to curse. And the other ברייתא braita
says you're not prohibited to do either, okay, because they're both an
issue of עמך. amcha. Alright, so both of them hold that they're
Jewish and everybody agrees that therefore because they're not עושה מעשה עמך,
oseh ma'aseh amcha, you are not prohibited in cursing. And the discussion
is: does it also mean that you're not prohibited in hitting? By
the way, I should just say, I'm waiting for somebody to ask
me the question. One minute. If my ox gores their ox I
have to pay them, but I'm allowed to hit them? So there's
a difference between allowed and liable in payment. The question we're dealing
with is do you transgress the prohibition when you hit or curse?
It's not the question about whether you actually would have to compensate.
Okay, compensation is a different point. Compensation is a בבא קמא Bava
Kamma point. Okay, but whether there is a prohibition, so now what
we said is very interesting. Within the prohibitions of hitting and cursing
a parent, and it applies even after the parent is dead and
applies like maybe even if you're trying to do a medical procedure
and so on, we actually have said that cursing doesn't apply if
the parent was not עושה מעשה עמך, oseh ma'aseh amecha, was not
a good upstanding halachic citizen or how you define that. And it
might be that even hitting doesn't apply in that case and that's
at least an issue that is debated, okay. And the same that's
true about a parent is true about a fellow Jew, okay. That
cursing doesn't apply if they're not עושה מעשה עמך, oseh ma'aseh amecha,
whether hitting is also would not apply, that's an issue of debate
and that was what was going on in the case by the
כותי. kusei. All right, we will end with this. Good luck.